We'll just wait another couple minutes until most people get in and then we'll get started I'm going to call the traffic Commission for November 11th 2025 to order it's
336 p.m. And we'll get started with the minutes of the previous meeting September 20 25 minute meeting minutes. Well, that's correct where we are. We are awaiting One other member here. He is we can we can officially get started and actually vote on the minutes Okay, it's a it's a it looks like it's a long agenda, but I don't think it's going to be that especially long I think many of these things are very interesting and will be straightforward for most of your consumption
Anyway, I've already called the meeting to order the first item on the agenda is the minutes of the previous meeting
there's been a there's been a motion is there a second motion in a second is there further discussion so there'll be that amendment to the minutes do we need
to second the amendment very good motion in a second to accept the minutes as
amended all in favor any opposed the motion carries thank you next we have staff project updates Cindy McCormick city engineer so we have a list of
projects that you know the city has been working generally providing this fall South Dukes that contractor started working there reducing the travel width by adding back in diagonal we have a couple intersection improvements at Queen and Farnham that are starting as well where there'll be a beacon added to that to improve did want to note vision zero and the safe streets for all grant we will be having it's a drop-in for open house we had related to our safe streets project so there'll be various projects that will be discussed there's a couple projects that had safe routes to school around for McCray school as well as presented really to bed there's a version study which we are very good
thank you very much Cindy are there any questions from the from the Commission regarding the question the projects that she presented um i know it's unusual to do so but
are there any questions from the public on what she just presented okay then we'll go straight into the action agenda first there's old business the item is the first item is item 29-2025
considering the request of angela peel regarding traffic in the 200 block of west grant street as the union community health center nears completion miss peel so just a very quick update on that we did meet with some residents from landis place and we did an observation on that one and the conclusion we came to based on what we heard from that meeting was just that we have some administrative actions that we can take so we don't need any action from the traffic
commission it's things like daylighting to improve visibility at some of the intersections improving pavement markings uh removal of a tree some minor things like that so um yeah we had a successful meeting with them and all of that you say can be done on an administrative level correct uh is miss peel here she is not no so so we can withdraw this from we can withdraw this from the agenda
going forward yes yes okay thank you very very much very greatly appreciated and often often some of the issues when we when we raise these issues at traffic commission some of them can
be done at the staff level by having exactly that kind of a meeting with the with the residents in
question or with with the intersection or part of the city in question so we very much appreciate being able to do it that way do we need to move this to be tabled removed it could be i guess
guess I'll make a motion to deny motion to deny any further discussion all in favor any opposed motion carries the second item is item 31-20 25
considering the request of Jessica Cardona to replace the stop sign at Fairview Avenue in Fremont Street miss Cardona can you
either speak closer to this and make sure that it's that it's activated hello yeah okay I'm sorry I don't see her here I mean she's the one to put the request
in but on I am the owner of the house that was hit twice here I mean I spoke at last meeting so okay do we have from from staff do we have a report on this item Thank You Ben commission Ben Hogan public works engineer for city of Lancaster. We took a review of potential all-way stop control at the intersection of Fairview and Fremont ahead of this meeting. So there's a few warrants in federal and state guidance to implement all-way stop control at an intersection or lead us to believe it could be justified. A few of them would be intersection site distance, traffic volume that travels through the intersection, crash history at the intersection, and then a few other various factors like pedestrian volume. So when we took a look at this intersection we found that sight distance for the northbound approach was adequate but for the southbound approach on the northwest corner of the
intersection vehicles are currently parking directly up to the crosswalk approximately two spaces that's creating a sight distance deficiency for southbound traffic they're not able to see eastbound traffic adequately on
Fairview Avenue as Fairview isn't stop controlled where Fremont north-south is free-flowing. We also took a look at crash history at the intersection. There were three relevant crashes that occurred within the past 12-month period of preceding September 2025. This doesn't meet the warrant for 12 months. However, if we look at 36 months of crash data, we had five
relevant crashes, and this does meet the threshold of five or more crashes that could be corrected by all-way stop control. We did observations of the intersection. I happened to notice that a few
vehicles were traveling the wrong direction on Fairview Avenue. We heard that in the complaint about this particular intersection that wrong-way driving is a frequent occurrence.
It's a little tough to tell with the current construction in the neighborhood. UGI has quite a number of projects going on out there at the moment. A lot of the streets are closed off from day to day, so it's tough to tell if that's, from the observations, if that's a
regular occurrence. It sounds like it may be, or if those few particular cars were just because of altered travel patterns because of those street closures. There are no other factors that I should
note that could lead toward all-way stop control and I'll also note that on our draft we're currently working in a revised high injury network. Our last update was in 2020 and this will be an
update we're expecting in 2025 or 2026 as a part of our Vision Zero plan. Those are our streets with the highest number of fatal and severe crashes. Fairview Avenue in its entirety is looking like it's going to be on that high injury network and we also have a program coming up the neighborhood slow zone program that we've mentioned in the past that will provide kind of systemic improvements in neighborhoods to slow
down traffic targeted on those smaller more local streets we think this would be a great candidate likely for that neighborhood slow zone program and we just like you to keep that in mind for this item as a result of the study the only factor that could warrant always stop control at the intersection would be that crash history for three years our recommendation because of that would be to deny the always stop control at the intersection and then look at additional improvements on the administrative level we were looking at
daylighting at the intersection using paint and flex posts some additional signage to clarify that it is a two-way stop and that traffic from the Fairview Avenue approach doesn't have to stop and then we were also looking to add do not
enter signage at the intersection to better clarify that it is a one-way
street in case that's an issue of confusion thank you so just for Clark
thank you very much Ben for that report out so just for clarification the intention even though the request was to place a stop sign at Fairview Avenue at Fremont the recommendation is to not put a stop sign but to add several other
elements in the in the toolbox for safe streets to be able to make it safer greater vision visibility and to let people know by signage that it is a one-way street or what with the directionality of traffic should go etc that's correct the guidance is very strict about always stop control should be applied sparingly and on a case-by-case basis one block over is Fairview and Union that's a very similar intersection only difference really is that southbound traffic is or the northern approach is two-way compared to this intersection where the northern approach is just one way so we would want consistency in the application and if this were to be approved as an always
stop I think our concern would be that then you would be looking for an always stop one block over at Fairview in Union so there's other safety benefits that we can get or we can get similar safety benefits as an always stop by doing other things such as traffic calming in the neighborhood we think that neighborhood slow zone would be a great great project for this area very good thank you very very much for that clarification thank you are there any other questions from the commission or comments from the commission i have a question about um about speed humps or raised pedestrian crossings are
those similarly restricted by warrants like were those considered why is that something that would you know also slow down traffic and prevent some of these crashes i would certainly slow down
traffic speed humps are a great idea that would be paired in our neighborhood slow zone program
likely along fairview avenue to try to bring traffic around 20 to 15 miles an hour in that area rather than 25 or exceeding that speed limit raised crossings raised intersections have quite a large price tag to them so for a project like this we'd probably just be looking at speed humps or something similar there's no specific warrants other than the criteria of the street that would apply to that but this is really a a good candidate location for that thank you very much thank you do you know you're going to ask a
question that is correct that's been a motion you're making that a motion there's been a motion is there a second motion in a second is there any further discussion at the Commission level any comments from the public on this item please and I should have encouraged you to do so before indicate your name and block of residents
well my name is a world of Valencia and I own the property at seven six seven six six Fremont Street
thank you well thank you guys for listening and thank you for that report I'm glad at least
something is being done if anything and I did want to mention also what he was saying about
the going up the wrong way I don't know if it's something that you saw or was it the videos I sent
in the videos okay okay this is an occurrence that happens daily the videos that I sent in were just I visit my parents weekly so this is just me getting there and seeing happened just to see it and then getting you know the videotape from it and in one of them I'm not sure if you guys had an opportunity to see it there was a near miss on one like and this i even have another one that just happened november again again i was just getting it to my parents house so i don't know why these vehicles are going up the wrong way i don't think it's that they don't know because this vehicle is parked on either side of the street so obviously they know that this is a one
way um i think it's just an easier way for them instead of going the whole way around the block
um but yeah i'm happy that at least if it's not the stop sign there's something else that's you
know hopefully gonna be done about it so thank you for that thank you very much as well Ben can you speak for just a moment on how the proposed remedies will
address the one way or the wrong way traffic yeah so we would be installing do not enter signage on the backside of traffic signposts at the intersection to face I guess it would be the westbound direction for traffic on Fairview Avenue
to kind of alert them in case it's a mistake that they're traveling the wrong direction and then we would also hope if we're doing intersection daylighting at the intersection we can kind of tighten up those corners to make it inconvenient to turn the wrong direction onto the street and also narrow that travel way
to make it very apparent that it's a one-way street very good again one of the principles we like to work on is passive enforcement rather than active
any other further questions or comments hearing none there's a motion on the
table and a second all in favor aye any opposed the motion passes thank you very very much the next item on the action agenda for old business is item 32 of 2025 considering the request of Tiffany Weicker to add a stop sign to 600 block of North Shippen Street is Miss Weiger Weicker present is there a report if it
was denied then then this should this is an item that should not be on the agenda our apologies for that the next item on the agenda is item 33-20 25 considering the request of this rot Mulu geta to add a turning lane on Hershey Avenue and Waubank Road. Is Bisrath present? Is there a report out on this one? You may want to sit on
the other side. Yeah, so we don't have a formal report before you. What I will say is we're currently working on traffic signal improvements at that intersection to both improve pedestrian safety and improve safety for vehicles. We're installing pedestrian signals there where they don't exist now as a part of that work we are going to buffer the bike lane as it approaches the intersection and have some delineators in the middle there because of that the there isn't adequate space to put a turn lane at the
intersection we counted vehicle volumes for the intersection which is typically
how it's determined if a turn lane is justified at the intersection or not it does not meet those warrants to have a turn lane installed so we would recommend that a turn lane not be installed at this time okay but we don't need if mr i'm assuming i apologize to all uh miss mr bisrat is not present uh we're not taking action unless he comes if he doesn't come to the next meeting then we would this is the second oh so we can we can elect
to do it administer to do what we want wish administratively and need not take action on on his request okay thank you thank you very much Ben so yes motion in a second any further discussion any further comment from the public hearing
none all in favor aye any opposed that motion carries now this brings us into
new business the first item in new under new businesses item 39-20 25 the broad and Chesapeake project adding bi-directional bicycle lanes which
results in loss of parking bus stop right relocations and large truck turning restrictions at specific intersections Emma hum from from our public right-of-way division will be making this presentation is that correct Emma okay I gave him one of them hi there uh okay so this is the broad and Chesapeake street project this is about 1.6 miles of improvements this street is being repaved it was on our repavement plan and so that is part of the impetus for some of the redesign elements it's also on our active transportation plan to add a separated bicycle facility so we are adding bi-directional
bicycle lanes on the southern side of the street so there are the project overall technically isn't subject to traffic commission review but there are three specific issues resulting from
the plan that are subject to traffic commission review i'll just note also that we had a public meeting on this last night thanks phillip attended we did get some feedback so there may be minor adjustments but at this point this project is slated to go to construction in 2026 2027. um so the two the two or three issues i'm sorry that are relevant to traffic commission oversight the first one is turning so prohibiting the turning of vehicles at intersections we are looking to prohibit turning of trucks over 50 feet and I might turn this one over to Ben but at the intersection of South Queen and Chesapeake so this is a little bit confusing to look at but this is actually three street segments that you're looking at so in the top left is the intersection of Queen and Chesapeake. So the bicycle lane comes in to intersect with Queen and then we have sort of enhanced crosswalks and a curb bump out to improve visibility and reduce the crossing distance for pedestrians. So we would be looking to disallow trucks from
taking the turn here because of that larger bump out thanks I just want to chime in a bit about that we're prohibiting the largest size vehicles
trucks with 53 foot trailers that you would typically see on the interstate we need to accommodate those turning movements at the intersection which requires quite large curb radii and in turn very long pedestrian crossings so
at this intersection we're proposing a curb bump out to kind of protect
bicyclists at the intersection and also shorten the pedestrian crossing distance as well throughout the project we're narrowing the travel lanes to pretty much the minimum standard size of 10 to 11
feet and as a part of that in coordination with the designer of the project they hadn't thought
that it was appropriate to have full-size trucks traversing broad chesapeake streets so as a part of that we would like to request a truck restriction for trucks over 50 feet in length making the right turn from queen to chesapeake street do do we as commission want to talk about each of the items in sequence or all together i mean if we're making motions i think i would
rather i mean or we can do separate ones but at the end after we've been thinking about but yeah if there are questions are there questions about what has been proposed for the second for the first intervention you know there's some history that goes with this uh when route 30 was under construction back in the 90s there was a plan to close off Lititz Pike in Oregon to rebuild the bridges across there and they wanted to divert through the city using
Broad Street and Chesapeake Street so when we did go to the meeting the first comments were
the two houses that were at the corner right and as soon as that the PennDOT said no then we said scrapped the plan and then that's where the traffic light came on on route that was the results because if they didn't want to do that then the rest of the using broad saying Broad Street doesn't belong to the state it's city on city yeah and they were going to do that I said you have to do that you would have to do this yeah we gave them several points on on the traffic issues on Chesapeake and Broad Street they weren't they weren't going to do anything other than existing conditions okay anything further from the Commission just do we have a sense that that movement is being used by a large number of tractor-trailer
trucks right now yeah so it's not used by a terrible number of trucks I don't have the exact numbers in front of me here but we did turning movement counts at the intersection of Queen and Chesapeake and checked the truck percentage that turns right onto Chesapeake from Queen. The vast majority of trucks continue north onto Queen Street and then either make, it's about a 50-50 split, those that make a right onto Church and then to Lyme and those that continue straight through on Queen Street. We can't break out from that what number of those trucks would have been restricted under this. What I will say is while we were developing the project in aerial imagery, we did notice one full-size truck that had a 53-foot trailer that would have been restricted under this. Our intent with this restriction is that if they're coming northbound into the city, that they would continue on to US-222, North Lyme Street, and out of the city to the north.
That is a great question. I would expect it to end probably at Duke Street, South Duke Street. That's also a challenging turn, so we could also take it to King Street.
Yeah, they would have to make the movement somewhere south of the city. There's not many options to the south. Or they could continue from Queen Street to Church to Lyme and then over to King. It's a very challenging turn.
Yeah. Yeah.
Especially for those huge trucks.
Yeah. Any further discussion or comment about what needs to be addressed? Maybe identifying an alternate? well my my other reason the thing that prompted my question is are there any user like any industries or anything in that stretch that take regular deliveries by those large trucks
uh at a cursory review we didn't see any businesses that would uh use trucks of those size um we expect that trucks within the city are typically using the 40 foot trailers instead
the shorter wheelbase vehicles and just to clarify i mean the restriction is only for the turn at that intersection it's not it's not to restrict trucks on on the street. Yeah I apologize just that one movement.
Any further discussion on this item. Let's go on to the next to the next item for consideration.
Emma.
Sure so the next two are just slightly adjusted bus stops. There is a bus route that heads southbound on Broad and then continuing on to Chesapeake so the stop and the area of south broad and circle avenue which uh mindy if you could go to the next page of this yeah so at the top sort of in the center right now there is a bus stop this project would add a new crosswalk a small pedestrian island and then sort of a median island as well that would help to whoops yep now it's to the sorry I know it's because you make it a little bigger and focus in on the top center there we go all right so essentially we're just asking to move this bus stop back 100 feet L'Oreal's cog from SCTA is here and I believe she and Ben did communicate about that proposed change anything else you want to add to that one yeah I think that'll make for a much safer situation sort of for everyone at that location and then the other stop is just a slight adjustment the stop in the area of Stevens Avenue and Chesapeake Street near the Thaddeus Stevens Griner campus which is a little bit further up the hill on Chesapeake Street here just moving the bus stop back further sort of towards the east south into an area with a
a narrow shoulder and no on-street parking and it out of the access drive isn't it right now
currently sort of in an access drive when that building was built that bus stop was not adjusted so very minor changes there laurie do you want to say anything or that one we're not making much
changes to the stop itself. Other people may not have heard the stop at Claremont. Yes, the stop at South Broad Street and Claremont Avenue. That would be the top right corner or center left
corner of your screen. We're just expanding that bus stop a bit to meet the regulations for recommended bus stop size. A lot of our stops throughout the city are pretty small and they don't allow for the bus to fully get out of the crosswalk to the curb and then merge back into traffic so with this one we're taking uh we are asking to take a bit more parking at that bus stop but no relocation of the bus stop itself any comments or questions from the commission
okay and then go to the third item sure so the final issue is that on this map you can see there
are areas that are in orange so those are areas that would become parking prohibited areas so most of that parking would be most of those areas would be parking prohibited to facilitate the bi-directional bicycle lane on the south side of the street there are a couple of segments on the northern side of the street that are meant to improve visibility to give the bus stop a little bit more space where we're adding crosswalks just sort of adding adding some space there you'll notice the blue lines parking is being maintained in those areas it's just being pushed pushed to the north a little bit so the request here is to officially designate parking prohibited areas and all the areas that are orange most of which are the would be the new bi-directional bicycle lanes before I go
go to you is there are other questions or comments from the Commission the parking authority wants to be heard which can you come up to the mic okay I
i hope so you might as well keith radicek lakers parking authority how many net spaces would have
to be uh reduced in this model do i go back to larry and go we're losing 10 spaces we're losing 20 spaces we're losing five spaces do we know that number none of these spaces are metered so they're just empty spaces right they're not regulated anyway there's no residential
permit parking there's no metered parking okay so i did thank you um was i mistaken that part of the advantage is to be able to provide some drop-off space or is that a different location
near the school i think the main advantage near the school was eliminating sort of any parking on the south side of the street because there's a lot of um there's some spaces that are used sort of to drop off children but there's no sidewalk on that side of the street and there's So there's a lot of mid block crossing and it's kind of a dangerous crossing area trying to discourage any kind of very good Very good. Thank you very much for that
Are there any more comments about what comments or questions about this third item? Are there comments or questions about any of the items from the public? So what I'm I'm assuming unless there's anything that needs to be adjusted. I think the first item that was talked about was it's not restricting the trucks it's just restricting the turn at that intersection so I I'm happy to entertain a motion to to approve this
recommendation I usually don't initiate the motion and I guess I'm looking for For it to be an approval of the entire agenda item
very good we have a motion do we have a second a second we have a motion in a second is there any further discussion at the Commission level any further discussion at the public level please Lori the restricted right turn I thought it was only for 53 foot trucks it's not for all traffic correct correct okay the motion did not indicate it just said right turn prohibition which that is correct correction that you are making it is intended to 53 trucks greater than
50 feet and you know can you use your mic yeah that's it'll be for the
restriction of the truck turning radius so the the motion has been amended to clarify that it's the turning radius of trucks of 50 feet or longer that's
correct yes okay is there a second to that amendment I'll second the amendment we have a new motion revised motion thank you for very much for that clarification are there any further comments or questions hearing none all in favor any opposed that motion carries thank you very very much for all that work and for making sure that we're staying on the straight and narrow in terms of the things that need to be approved rather than just ignoring or
forgetting which ones are of our purview the next item on the new business action agenda is item 40 dash 2025 considering the request of pamela dintaman to add an all-way stop at west lemon
street and nori and north mary street is miss dintaman here please am i getting your name
correct thank you thank you for adding this to the agenda today i think there are others here who might want to and but i'll kick it off um i live at 507 west lemon so i face the intersection
we're looking at and i i've never seen it that empty which is which is great maybe it's a sign of the future but um what i've been noticing is the cars from north mary which are coming south to north um periodically somebody is uh stop generally they stop and then proceed through the intersection without looking both ways. There's a lot of near misses happening and if I try to understand it as a lay person I understand that they've come through a series of one-way crossings. They've crossed orange, chestnut, walnut and lemon is the first one where they have two directions coming. So whether it's that they're not catching on that there's two directions or the bike lane may be obstructing some visibility I'm not sure I'm really glad for the businesses that are thriving not only the ice cream shop there but the Kevlar restaurant but that adds a lot of in-and-out traffic too I'm not sure a
four-way stop is the answer that's just one of the things I put in my note
somehow I'd like to see attached to the stop sign something that alerts people someone else yes does anyone else want to speak to this item as well please come forward and again
state your name in the block uh the block that you live on uh yeah so i am the uh owner of cablar
miko um and pamela had reached out to us about uh about the issue and i just recently a couple weeks prior heard from my staff just talking about how they've observed like like she said near misses car crashes screeching tires all that sort of stuff a lot of it is obviously uh you know it's just a busier area now that we have our business there you get a lot of the college kids going to splits and giggles it's just a very active uh crosswalk uh so there's a lot of people constantly moving around there might we have you know so many spots in our lot might be parking elsewhere walking over walking to the ice cream shop you know i'm sure when brandy's eventually opens you know it'll just add to it um but yeah i'm not sure what the solution is but here to support our team noticed the same things that she noticed so when she reached out we thought it was pertinent um you know i personally you know drive up mary consistently and drive down the other one ways and i always feel a little little sketchy whether it's lemon
or chestnut or you know they're all kind of treated like three ways it kind of even if it's a one way even i feel like i can kind of see sort of see i think that's everybody and then sometimes somebody's cruising at 45 miles an hour and it's hard to you know hard to see that car but uh but yeah we'd love to come to some sort of resolution that makes it safer very good thank you very very much is anyone else wanting to speak on this item from the
public in the introduction to the issue yes please and again your name and block of residence hey I'm Steve Farina I live on the 400 block of Lancaster Avenue so
I'm like to the left of this and down a little it is a really busy intersection There's a ton of kids. My wife and I just started letting our 12-year-old walk there by herself. It's a really busy intersection, especially with the ice cream shop. They pull a lot of children in. With Cabellar, they pull a lot of everybody else in. With Brandy's right
there, there's been that dumpster blocking a good portion of that corner on Mary. There used to be crossing guards there probably 10, 12 years ago in the mornings and afternoons for school children. That hasn't been there in a long time. There was a man, Chuck Layman,
who was hit and killed there in 2015 in a hit and run. So it is, they go fast on Lemon Street in both directions.
And like one of the previous comments said, With it being the first two-way street,
it's not a spot where people really stop and look. I've also seen two or three, at least two,
maybe three people turn the wrong way onto Mary off Lemons.
So I think a four-way stop would be a good way to just get people to stop and think
before they try to turn the wrong way
past the ice cream shop on Mary Street.
That's all.
you very very much um ben at the staff level did we do any review of this can you speak to that sure so again we reviewed this intersection based off of federal and state criteria for implementing always stop control there's a few different factors as a part of that traffic volume site distance crash history and then the other factors so we spent four hours observing the intersection collecting turning movement counts at the intersection i did see a few close calls during that time traffic on lemon street they couldn't see uh or sorry traffic on mary street pulling out not able to see traffic approaching on lemon street luckily no incidents based on site distance we already have pretty good restrictions at the intersection from when the lemon street project was completed for eastbound connector the bike facility through there good daylighting at the intersection based off of traffic volumes that were collected does not meet the volume threshold to implement always stop control based off of crash history
that's both reportable and non-reportable crashes at the intersection there were two relevant
crashes that occurred in a 12-month period preceding its peak which was july 2024 this does not meet the warrant of four more four relevant crashes occurred in a 36-month period preceding July 2024. That also doesn't meet the warrant of five plus crashes. What I will say though is one of the other factors that I mentioned in the MUTCD is that where pedestrian and or bicyclist movements support the installation of all-way stop control, an intersection could neighborhood with both commercial and residential uses. When those turning movement counts were collected, that was a Tuesday and a Wednesday. So Cabellar was closed. Brandy's Pub is still closed for long-term renovations so we'd expect much higher pedestrian volumes in the future even so with those two businesses being closed we saw a very very high pedestrian volume at the intersection it was uh in a two-hour period we observed two hours a.m two hours p.m it ranged
from about 60 to 80 pedestrians per hour navigating the intersection so quite a substantial amount based on that we think always stop control could be justified at the intersection but we would certainly leave it up to the commission whether or not that is implemented thank you very very much i'm going to open it to the commission for comment yeah i do uh have if we do go with this if you can make a point of speaking into the uh as we uh if we do go and uh make uh approval on uh the making it an all-way stop would this be a candidate uh because of the nature of that neighborhood that the bus stops that mean the uh stop signs could be uh leds with the solar version that i see out there can i uh i'd love to chime in on that so there's a
certain process for converting intersections to always stop control in pendoc guidance what we would have to do for that is we would have to add a blinking red beacon above the stop sign you may have seen those at some other intersections throughout the city those are supposed to be temporary as people adjust to the change we'd also be putting pavement markings on the ground to alert that stop ahead and then also stop bars at the intersection what about the LED stop signs yeah we haven't trialed those anywhere in the city yet it certainly could be a location that we test them out at I've seen it work successfully in other communities that's
because I figured that would be a location because I've even with the stop signs on lemon street i can see blow throughs yeah it's a that's a good idea okay other comments or questions comment is there a recommendation are there comments or questions from the public let
me ask that joe sitzel i also live on the 400 block of lancaster avenue next to steve so i think he said most of it i just wanted to ask and put it under consideration there's a also some sort of metal bike stop i don't know what it is pamela maybe you know the history there but that also blocks kind of like the view look to the right it's in front of splits and giggles does anyone know if I don't know what that's for I don't think it's used that much it's a bike rack okay but I do think that impedes viewing also I have a two-year-old I go to the ice cream shop often and we cross over the road to cab or often and that also sort of impedes the view of pedestrians crossing to see if cars are coming down Lancaster of coming down lemon so I just want to mention that for further consideration and say I also support you know a stop sign here I think it would help pedestrians any other comments a question
from Ben maybe which is so you talked about the warrants in addition to a a potential always stop are there any other changes that you would recommend or take care of at the staff level other than like assuming we proved the stop you talked about the things that would go with that as a sure helping people
adjust but are there any other recommendations you have I think if we were to implement always stop control we probably wouldn't do anything other than what I had mentioned the additional supplements just to bring attention to the stop sign we might look at a few additional flex posts in the intersection. I think the corner with Cabellar doesn't have them currently. We didn't put them on every corner with the Lemon Street project. So I think there could be additional corners where that makes sense. As an alternate to always stop control, what I've seen work successfully is speed humps kind of spaced near the intersection, but on either side of it. And then that slows the traffic entering the intersection. But if we were to implement always stop control, I don't think would be appropriate coupled with the stop sign any other comments or questions regarding the
design the enforcement the implementation i i do have um maybe some concerns just with the fact that there are no other stop signs along lemon street so sort of driver expectation would
be a concern i mean we have done the cross traffic does not stop or i'm not sure if there's look
could be done and you say in the interim as a trial questions commentary wishes proposals yeah I would just add bikes through that regularly along that bike lane and it definitely is a high traffic area I don't know I would like to see something I hearing a four-way stop makes sense kind of inclines me towards approving it it is true that there are no other I'm trying to think of my bike right along that road and I don't think there are no other four there are no other stops on Lemon Street so it would be like a little bit on incongruous but I don't know I still think it might be worth it yes please as you mentioned flashing red light or something that sometimes calls attention to the four-way stop there there are no four-way stop signs but there are the stoplights at Charlotte and so perhaps a light above it would call attention to it I'm glad for the consideration you're giving to it and it's welcome to hear
the count of pedestrians that you found on a non busy time I appreciate your consideration of this so does someone want to make a recommendation I mean I
would I'm inclined to move to approve the request for an all-way stop I moved to I moved to approve the request of 40 2025 for an all-way stop at the intersection of West Lemon Street and North Mary Street there's a motion and a second is there further discussion at the Commission level is there is there a concern about the either the precedent being set or that it that it I mean
we've heard very clearly what the what the conditions are that would not have
warranted having a stop sign but that under special considerations given this
the unique circumstances here that it's it's allowed to be encountered and even though there's no other stop four-way stop or intersection at this I mean at this street there are two other signaled intersections nearby are any of those of
concern are those things we need to either put in a context or understand differently there's also the school uh people walk into school uh both up to wharton and also the reynolds so that that's another uh consideration to take and i'm not sure what the status with the school district uh is with having school crossing guards to get their work school crossing guards i think up until probably the last year of two years ago i haven't seen one
recently and is it consistent with the safe with safe routes to school program
and is that apply in this particular area yeah I guess that's what they I do have concerns about not wanting to set a precedent for installing every problem but that's not to say we haven't approved stop signs related to pedestrian these the alternate solution you had proposed which was speed speed hump was a full speed humps no the speed controls so is there any further FOR THE DISCUSSION AT THE COMMISSION LEVEL ABOUT EITHER THIS AS THE SOLUTION OR ENTERTAINING OTHER OPTIONS? I THINK OTHER OPTIONS NEED TO BE ENTERTAINED. I THINK YOU HAVE TO LOOK AT THE AREA AS A WHOLE, NOT JUST THIS ONE INTERSECTION. I THINK THERE ARE OTHER DYNAMICS THERE. YES, THIS INTERSECTION IS PROBLEMATIC, BUT PINE STREET IS JUST AS PROBLEMATIC. SO HOW THEN PUTTING A STOP SIGN UP HERE, HOW DOES THAT AFFECT PINE STREET, THE PINE STREET AND LEMON STREET INTERSECTION? I just think that there has to be a further look at all of Lemon Street from Mulberry all the way up to College Avenue. And the kinds of things one would similar to other studies that we've done before we
would be monitoring use would be we'd be asking certain key questions about how it could be
used what what a particular device or intersection element might be and what its effect might and then come back and report to the commission yes because everything once you implement one thing it's going to affect the next thing so you solve one problem but you create two other problems and we don't want to create two other problems just by putting in a stop sign it seems like a reasonable solution but when you put bike lanes in it's obviously affected the whole dynamic of lemon Street there so you fix one problem but yet you create another problem so I think it has to be looked at as a whole and it would not prohibit the consideration of the of the stop signs in the future it would just be within the context of greater consideration and a more studied way of looking at the at the set of streets well then I can make an amendment to table this to table uh 40 20 20 25. there's been an amendment to table it's amended from the uh doing a stop sign just to get the to do the study you know in order to do the study right i wouldn't be opposed to that i i mean the point is well taken pine street is similar a lot of you know there are a couple other streets so this one probably is the most traffic just because the businesses are all at that intersection but i wouldn't be opposed to learning more about and is this is this work that could be done within the next before the next traffic commission meeting i would believe so just looking at intersection control of the other intersections
between mulberry and college that's something we could do within the next two months for the january meeting and be able to make recommendations then based on the results of that study yeah i
I believe so so there's a motion on the table is there a second I mean one was the it was an amendment should it be withdrawn should your motion first be withdrawn yeah well it sounds like a new motion so I'll withdraw my motion in favor of tabling agenda item 2025 40 2025 till the January traffic Commission okay um so then there's a motion on the table is there a second i'll second a motion in a second is there further discussion about the new motion which is to do gender data study and entertain
recommendations for the january traffic commission meeting and please and comments from and other comments from the public as well i will respect your decision if you go that way i wonder whether
it can be a both and where there would be movement on this intersection because of the amount of business traffic and pedestrian traffic and an overall assessment be done over the next several months right exactly the first the implication of the first part of that request would be yes my first reaction would be that once one installs the the device the stop sign you you've changed change the dynamic and you've set the precedent
without having had the study as as a benefit but I want to turn open it to
the Commission as well just in case I may be misunderstanding it well the one thing that seems like it could maybe happen in the interim is at the administrative level just to see if there is a sign that's available it says look both ways for coming up Mary because that is gonna be a problem with her without a stop sign okay any other comments from the public on this item so there's a motion to be able to table this to entertain a study with recommendations that will come to the traffic Commission in January all in favor any opposed the motion carries thank you very very much and thank you for bringing this not only to our attention but being able to entertain the the nuances of the challenge the next item on the agenda is item 41 dash
2025 considering the request of Bennett crumbling to address speed and parking on Buchanan Avenue is mr. crumbling present okay so mr. crumbling is not present the table 41 2025 motion to table is there a second second is there any further discussion and it's it's often our practice that if the person
requesting it is not present to be able to have the conversation we would table it until they can be present or until a second call when they're not present so all in favor any opposed that item is tabled the next item on the agenda is
item 42-20 25 considering the request of Matt shields from the school district of lancaster to add bus loading unloading area from 7 30 to 8 15 a.m and 1 30 to 2 45 p.m at 600 rockland street hi matt how are you good evening thank you uh so uh we're here uh for the request we struggle at our morning arrival and and more so in the afternoon with pickup because there's parking on both sides of the street so our buses are not able to get curbside so they are often parked in the drive lane which forces vehicles to travel around them into
oncoming traffic at times so our request is to limit parking if possible along the curb during certain hours of the day for our arrival and pickup of the students to make it safer for everyone not just our students any did you want
to add something to this I believe there had been some discussion about this before on site during a pickup time yeah they are the buses there's numerous
buses that pick up children at this I think just allocating that curb space stirring and the besides enforcement the only key change would be making markings on the is there any further discussion at the Commission level for regarding this request sergeant you had spoke you had spoken to them about this before as well it's definitely a need for the school my only concern is the enforcement of it so because of those times of day and the limited staff that can come out and enforce the actual parking regulations that will be my greater concern I'm assuming there are no crossing guards at this at this school of this intersection any other comments or questions or ways of addressing those concerns so i do have a question um was dolphin street ever considered for the the bus pickup and drop and what were the pluses and minuses of that consideration the
biggest consideration for the principal there and sergeant summerall knows the history he's been in that building quite a bit over the years more so than we have but the biggest consideration
is is those kids and students in those buildings have very high needs um i'm sorry can you speak into the mic i'm sorry those students in that building have very high needs and because of that they have to institute certain internal and external plans sometimes not only to keep
them separated but to make sure that they get to the buses safely and they go through different
routes within the building to get to different locations some of them probably you do believe it from what you've heard in the past maybe we'll have one kid who gets on one bus and another kid who gets on another bus and they go to different locations but there are specific reasons for that most of them are behavioral they have to do with IEPs and certain behavioral plans that they're dealing with and sergeant is well aware of what goes on in that building so we're doing our best to kind of alleviate any sort of dangerous situation specifically with kids running out into traffic or perhaps interacting with each other and unfortunate things happening so if there's a lot of planning that goes into
that so if I can understand it correctly the dolphin as an option just means that
the students would be too far away from their destination and would require more supervision with limited staff correct we're already very short staff this sergeant alluded to in that building and district-wide so there is a big burden as far as trying to monitor and control their behavior and that just would put an unnecessary burden on them using that location as
far as pick up and drop off so they figured out that that rocklin street entrance is probably the
most direct and easiest route for those kids to get directly onto the bus okay
there's a lot of is there anything else from either staff or from the from the
Commission that to be shared about this particular item any comments from the public does someone want to make a recommendation I'll make a motion to approve 42 2025 there's been a motion in a second any further discussion anything further from the public hearing none all in favor aye any opposed the motion
carries is there any is there any sense of how long this may take to make those kinds of adjustments very good thank you very very much the next item is item 43
dash 2025 considering the request of Randy Doutrick of Doutrick engineering
to present land development plans at 558 Longfellow Drive Mr. Doutrick thank you for your patience my name is Randy Doutrick I completed the land development plans for 558 Longfellow we're proposing a four unit apartment building there each unit will have three bedrooms and we're required have one parking space per unit but we actually have seven parking spaces and one ada parking space and we the existing site if you look at is line with all massive pine trees that's all been cleared out already for the for the proposed sidewalk and the street trees we are in our third review with the city and we're down to pretty minimal comments and so i just came to the Commission's meeting is seen by any concerns
Anything further that you wanted to present regarding this item anything further that you wanted to present regarding this item
Cindy was there some review by staff
And, yeah, we don't – this has, yeah, been vetted through a driveway apron engineering stand. And how far through the development process is this? We have conservation approval. We're in our third review of the city. So we're getting close now. And there's no impediment to making the traffic commission approval to the land development approval? I see Lauren is present. I mean this is one of the requirements for their land okay very good is there anything further that to be submitted or shared by staff regarding this particular item so are there any questions from the Commission regarding this item what do we need to approve is there like a parking spot that's gonna get removed for that driveway or something no we're we approved driveway openings if it's for generally we have a policy that staff at the staff level will approve driveways for three units or less if it's with if it's more than that then it would like if it's a commercial driveway or some other higher use driveway than the traffic any further comments or questions at the
Commission level any comments or questions from the public hearing none do I hear a motion make a motion to approve 43 2025 I hear a motion do I
hear a second second there's been a motion in the second is there any further discussion any further comment from the public hearing none all in favor any opposed the motion carries thank you very very much thank you for
your presentation as I understand it item 44 2025 has been withdrawn from the current agenda and so the next item on the agenda is item 45-2025 consider the request of Benjamin Morton of RGS associates to present land development
plans on behalf of Lancaster Lebanon Habitat for Humanity to build
owner-occupied multi-family housing units at 913 Wheatland Avenue I apologize
can you speak a little bit closer sure microphone thank you um so we are here to talk about 913 wheatland avenue with eight multi-family housing units being proposed there this we is a land development project so much like the last one you were talking about we're really looking here for your approval that can be contingent upon the detailed design review
that will occur during the land development review process we did submit a sketch plan
back in the spring have been working through particularly elements related to storm water management and are actually going to be submitting the prelim final plans tomorrow but with your two-month window on meetings i wanted to to get here ahead of the january meeting because we're hoping for an expeditious approval so that we can get eight more affordable housing units starting construction in the early part of next year. So with this request there are three access drives currently within the project area. Two of them we're looking to reconstruct and slightly modify
and then one of them will be removed. I think those exhibits nothing's changed in terms of the design but I added a little more color just because there's a common alley here and in case
things get a little bit confusing about the project that thought that could be helpful so of the drives starting Easter most there's what we're calling access
Drive a this is currently a one-way enter only access drive that connects to a common alley which serves the pocketbooks bookstore multi-family residence and uh two single family residences it goes on the east side of the site then the north side of the site i guess on paper it extends further west but the pavement and the properties that can actually access it are just limited to the ones i mentioned at that point then the way the site functions now vehicles either enter the parking lot or the drive on the west side of the site and exit from either of the other two access drives so access drive b on the west side which is one that we're looking to to keep as well is exit only as is access drive c in the middle which we're looking to remove i think if you want to switch to the proposed condition so there for both of the access drives that are going to remain they're being widened slightly just so they relate better to the width of the common alley as it's being modified here and then in terms of the actual construction of it we're going to be providing the five foot wide pedestrian access route that has a two percent cross slope with you know a concrete drive apron so for the on the common alley side because of how that interacts with the neighboring properties we're providing only the most minor changes in the grading just to accommodate that 2% slope and then on the west side there is some regrading happening because we have a pedestrian access route that's sharing that drive around to the rear so it will be staying under 5% along that length is
there anything further that you wanted to share or present no I think that's
good for now but if you have any questions happy to answer them sure has staff reviewed this project as well as Ben mentioned this has only been through
a sketch plan review so there hasn't been any kind of detailed review yet of the of the plans and which which suggests that not that you have any intention to make major changes but it suggests that there may be some changes as the as this plan evolves is there any input that you're specifically looking for in terms of either a sense of the Commission or if there's any red flags or items that might be problematic I don't think so and I think what we'd be looking for again is you know approval of the removal of the middle drive and
the approval of these driveways as they're shown here and if there were to
be if there were to be major modifications to them I think we'd be
looking at you know a major changes to the entire site program so we'd be back here and re envisioning the process anyway would we be seeing you at the
once the approval of the land development process is complete they're asking for a conditional approval now for the driveways do we have any objection to providing that I guess what is your schedule for I guess what is your hope for as far as the schedule for the land development that you're wanting approval now I mean we're with when we're submitting and just kind of the amount of back and forth we've had on a number of items particularly around the stormwater I mean our our hope is to try to keep this approval within the actual 90 day turnaround to get to conditional approval so you know I'm hopeful for being in front of planning commission in January and I feel as though you know we I know on
different projects in the past we've kind of ended up at this commission at different points in time
I think here where we felt it was prudent to to come and try and just accelerate this process so
we weren't then stuck with when to come back at the end potentially delaying it you know especially given that they're two existing driveways that that are really just being modified to improve some of the flow and at least from when we've done
this in the past if there are minor changes to the width or that sort of thing we did not anticipate that being an issue for the Commission to revisit
Andrew from Habitat for Humanity we've also been very much engaged with the resident neighbors both immediately adjacent and those across the street condo and condominiums across the street and down the street West End Avenue so forth I've been involved as part of this being one apart the satellites more or
less of the college Avenue project and redevelopment of Medical Center there's been a lot of interest in this and having the confidence of at least this is the site that we're gonna be working with and a traffic pattern will be working will give them some more comfort is we're going through the other steps and letting them engage and weigh in with us about the process so it'll help me is there anything else we need to be aware of in terms of that I guess I'm
just one so you've been directly I guess engaged are there any kind of agreements
with the the adjacent property owners that share access to this common alley that you're going to be using as the primary access we're just starting that
process we have been engaging we have been conversations with those folks they're along Marietta Avenue and the commercial property it's adjacent to two businesses several months ago we're reengaging with them right now to get the agreements because knowing what this lot traffic layout in the store now we
we know what the stormwater system is supposed to look like what we're really asking them in terms of uh everything from the alleyway access the liens and so forth and maintenance so that's the actual agreements are coming together and the other thing i i should mention is you know this
is the traffic pattern that's in place now but it's not formalized and so it is our intention it'll be on the plans that we're creating actually an access easement on habitats property to formalize the rights of the surrounding neighbors who are utilizing that route to be able to use that in the future so that's that's part of the discussion then i know some of the conversations that you had in the past about the common alley and getting approvals for that were actually
if anything more fraught because there was a time that the design was putting stormwater management
facilities within the common alley and so there were a lot more complications whereas now in terms
of the flow and functionality of the alley it's being improved some of the spacing in terms of cars that are parked opposite each other on it there's going to be more space than exists in in the current condition or we're actually eliminating some of the conflicts that came from parking that directly access the alley so right now the movement is you know even though like the common alley is 14 feet wide which a lot of city alleys could be two-way as being 14 feet wide is is the current movement that they do circulate around in a one-way fashion or is it being used as a two-way and that would be potentially limiting it is actually um signed and uh there are pavement markings indicating that it's one way okay that's not to say there aren't people who leave the bookstore and go out the other way but it is already signed and striped of course and but your intention is for it to be one way yes and in keeping with that that currently signed movement do do we know when in january the the the other meeting is not our
meeting well no i guess that's his his uh estimate of when they would like to be at the planning
Commission but there you've indicated you'll be submitting plans for the first time tomorrow right or okay I guess I just the other question I had related to the retaining wall is there currently a retaining wall or how is that yeah on
the western edge there's a retaining wall there proposed there is not but that's also something where we're proposing a temporary construction
easement and then some landscape restoration on that property to allow that to be installed so how high would that wall um it's only i'm trying to remember at most it's getting in the three foot range in some areas but a lot of it's less than that so is your your sites
elevated then yes so there were yeah i thought i saw there would need to be there's like guide rail or something yeah so here i'll just throw something out here it's it seems like there's
that there's a strong intention of what you want and some goals of how that gets addressed but that there's some details that still need to be resolved in order to make sure that that works properly I wouldn't want any proposed motion to suggest if approved to suggest that this is a permission to do anything more than than to get to the next stage of the planning process um so that if anything needs to get done in between or adjustments get made it's based on a if you will very strictly conditional approval not permit permission to do anything else like start construction demolition or anything like
that no so and certainly in in the past when we've come at sort of an earlier stage like this we've i believe the approval has been written to be that it's conditioned upon satisfaction of all
city staff and and now third-party review engineer comments and the approval of the city engineer for and that would be the condition and if we don't achieve those things then i mean i don't know that we'd come back here saying hey we want this approval even though we didn't achieve them i mean that's our intention is to work through the details of those items good thank you very
much for that just adding on to that um lancaster 11 and habitat for man he's turning 40 next year and the city of lancaster has been our longest standing partner uh it's you guys the city has a reputation of having higher standards and a little more rigor when it comes to some of the
land development process or even repairs we have embraced it intentionally and part of this process in fact working with rgs and some of our other partners on their line development stuff is
how do we delight you guys so that we're able to keep having impact here so we're very respectful
of making sure the ducks are in a row and communication with staff as well as the commission and so forth are very good standing so having heard all of that is there any further discussion or comment from the commission any from the public is there a willingness to make
a motion of some sort I'm moved to approve item 45 2025 to give RGS associates and Lancaster Lebanon Habitat for Humanity conditional approval for
the 913 Wheatland Avenue site conditional on final approval from the city there's been a motion is there a second second motion in a second is there any further comment or conditions the motion probably should just include that it would be it's approval of the two proposed driveway late locations and the elimination of the third driveway location I would accept that amendment amendment seconded you know yes okay amendment and seconded is there any further discussion or clarification necessary hearing none all in favor aye Hi any opposed The motion carries Thank you very very much. Thank you that concludes the action agenda
Are there public comments? This is an interesting time for public comments, I guess but In our agenda the next item is the public public comments are there any for any public comments Hearing none. We'll go to the consent agenda there are four items in the consent agenda one tentatively approving and installing handicapped parking item 46-20 25 the next which is a voluminous number of removed handicapped
parking locations item 47-20 25 this as I understand it is a regular inventorying of or de inventorying of Handicap spaces that are no longer necessary or where they have not been made the subsequent of applications
But it does look like a lot. It's just happens to be a lot at this particular moment. The next item is item 48 2025 Condition the conditional temporary parking permits having been issued by LPA One being a caregiver permit and the last item is item 49 dash 2025 the conditional temporary parking permits have asked for continuance
there's nothing nothing under that one so it's really just the first three make
a motion to approve 46 2025 through 49 2025 there's been a motion yes is there
a second second motion in a second is there any further discussion just again noting that 49 2025 has nothing in it true I would just approve 46 47 and 48 I'm fine with that I could be amended very good any any further discussion all in favor any opposed motion carries thank you very very much is there any additional business motion has been approved and seconded moved and seconded the meeting ends at 5 o 5 p.m. thank you very very much
the entire mary street just so that they can see it overhead i want yeah i want the expressway version